Hello everybody and welcome back to
active inference insights. Today I am
honored to be speaking with Professor
Mark Solms. Professor Solms is a
neuropsychologist and psychoanalyst best
known for his discovery of the full
brain mechanisms underlying dreams and
his integration of psychoanalytic
theories with modern neuroscience. More
recently, he's been focusing on active
inference and what it might bring to
bear on the hardest problem of them all,
consciousness.
Mark, thank you so much for joining me.
It's a yeah, as I said in the
introduction, it's a real honor and and
privilege.
It's it's great to be here, Darius.
Thanks very much.
So yeah, I mean, you have been in the
field of cognitive neuroscience for many
decades, but I guess have only recently
in the last 10 years or so have really
taken an interest in in active inference
and see you know, as many people have.
I think when I I read your book
The Hidden Spring, which is a wonderful
read,
and I think what I really liked about
it, I've been looking I'm very
interested in the hard problem and
trying to kind of see different
perspectives with which we can take to
to approach the hard problem.
And I've been looking for what I've been
calling the synthetic a priori of
consciousness. And what I mean by that
is, can we have a can we determine a
function
of cognition that needs to be conscious
a priori?
So for example, you could say attention.
Well, I can imagine
offline attention. I'm just sort of
pinging around without it being online.
And I thought you got very close and I I
will not say determine you know, I will
not say in a determined fashion because
David Chalmers will shout at me, but I
think you got very close with this
notion that affect is a good candidate
for what I would call the synthetic a
priori of consciousness.
Now, affect is
can be seen as a kind of loose term. So
I think where we might want to start is
just if you could give a kind of brief
definition of what you mean by affect
because obviously
maybe what you and Jaak Panksepp in
basic emotion theory think is affect
might differ from a constructionist the
term of affect and so on. So maybe if we
could just start laying down what affect
is before we get to consciousness.
Thank you. Yes, that's a good point to
start with because as you say, different
people do mean different things by that
term.
So what I mean by affect is first and
not not foremost, but first that it is
balanced. In other words, there's a
goodness and badness
to affect. And um
apropos of your opening remarks about a
a priori synthetic function,
the I think I should mention that the
goodness and badness of affect
applies only to the subject of the
affect. So it's good from my point of
view or bad from my point of view. It
doesn't mean that it is objectively or
universally good or bad. So an affective
state is a balanced state. It has
goodness and badness. The second
and perhaps this is the
when I said I
I don't want to say first and foremost
balanced because perhaps this is the
foremost characteristic is that it is
qualified by which I mean it has a
specific differentiated quality. There
are there are different affects. So
although all affects share the the
property of balance of goodness or
badness,
each affect has its own unique quality.
I don't mean to say that there aren't
intermediate forms of affect, but what I
mean is that the that the feeling of
hunger
is qualitatively different from the
feeling of thirst is qualitatively
different from the feeling of sleepiness
and so on.
And this is important
um
because you you you you can't you can't
say
I have
currently six out of 10 of sleepiness
and six out of 10 of thirst, therefore I
have
12 out of 20 of total
bodily need and all I need to do is
sleep.
If you if you did that, you would reduce
the the common
denominator
the the continuous variable of need, but
you would die. That is because
sleepiness and thirst are not the same
thing. They are qualitatively different.
They are categorical variables. So so
that's for me
the essential features of affect that
they're balanced,
which which implies they're subjective.
Their balance is subjective
and they are categorical
qualitatively differentiated states.
Okay, that's really useful. So I think
before we get into the qualitative
distinctions because I
you know, people may have seen your
debates with Lisa Feldman Barrett and
how deep that distinction runs was kind
of a sticking point in your in your
conversations. So before we go there, we
don't even necessarily need to go there.
I think the really interesting point
there is that good or badness is only
good or badness for a subject.
I've been thinking about this in terms
of relevance or prioritization that
whatever enters into the space of
consciousness is always prioritized or
relevant to the uh to the agent.
Now, I think there's a second question
that I will come to about are we not
putting the cart before the horse by
inferring the presence of an agent for
whom something is good or bad.
But before I go there,
folding in something like salience,
relevance or priority,
is that uh built into the goodness or
badness of the signal of the phenomenal
state
or is it or does it necessarily underlie
or underwrite that phenomenal state?
Um
the way I look on it
is that the
the underlying category is a category of
need. You do not feel all your needs.
So for example, your need for energy
resources
is met by your constantly burning up the
glucose uh
deposited in your adipose tissues.
But you don't feel anything.
Um
when that
need is prioritized, you then feel
hunger.
Um so the prioritization and the
becoming conscious of the need are I
think intimately bound up with each
other.
And so
what therefore does that say for this
kind of synthetic a priori of
consciousness in so far as if relevance
or salience or priority, whatever you
want to say,
is
it it's difficult to imagine being
conscious of something which is not in
some way salient to you.
Does that
put the that notion of salience
which we you know, I've been proposing
that consciousness might be something
like a relevance filter or a salience
filter,
would that make that function that
relevance function more akin to this
synthetic a priori of consciousness and
affect per se?
I think that the answer to that is bound
up with
what do we mean when we say we we are
prioritizing one need over another. It's
not it's not the prioritization is not
an end in itself. It's a prioritization
for action. You can't you can't do
everything
at once
in terms of
this prioritization
imperative and I'll explain what I mean
by that.
And it has everything to do with when
you say an a priori synthetic function,
it has everything to do with what
function we're talking about. So what
I'm saying
is that that function is not merely the
function of it's the feeling of the need
and what functionality is added by the
feeling of the need has everything to do
with the action bottleneck that I was
talking about. The prioritized need is
felt so that you can monitor how well or
badly you're doing in your attempts to
meet that need. The non-prioritized
needs are relegated to automaticity. The
actions that you perform in relation to
the non-prioritized needs do not have to
be felt because
they are being met or at least attempts
are being made to meet them outside of
consciousness by existing
fixed
policies.
The prioritized need which is felt, the
the function of the feeling is precisely
because you're in a state of
uncertainty.
The the
automaticity
doesn't cut it. Automaticity is
dangerous
because you don't know what to do. So
you're feeling your way through a novel
situation or through an unpredicted
situation and
the feeling tells you whether what
you're currently doing, the policy
you're currently following, whether it's
working or not. So it underwrites
choice.
It underwrites the possibility of
changing your mind on the fly.
And then of course, learning from the
experience which which which results in
the laying down of new predictions which
may in future be executed unconsciously.
It's while you it's sort of predictive
work in progress.
Automaticity is a is a good way of
describing it. And I want to make
explicit uh what I something in what
I've just said when I said that this
underwrites choice,
it means that it underwrites voluntary
action. So this is the mechanistic
difference in my view between voluntary
and automatic or autonomic action.
So yeah,
okay, that's that's interesting. There
are some things that I think we can fold
in from an active inference perspective
because um
you were talking you were talking about
almost meta-cognitive monitoring of how
well you're doing at minimizing free
energy. And that actually has been
fleshed out in in active inference as a
Joffroy and Core paper all the way back
in 2013. But recently people have been
talking about um
error dynamics, which is this awareness
of how well you're doing at minimizing
free energy over a span of time. And
they have associated that with valence.
My question here is more therefore
philosophical. So it's not really
pulling that in apart um
although there might be some people who
who would encourage me to do so, but
rather why couldn't that uh monitoring
be done offline?
So what is it about and this really gets
to the heart of this notion of a
synthetic prior of consciousness?
I can imagine in some sense a robot in
some thought experiment who was able to
offline attribute goodness or badness to
their experience
and use that in a functional manner to
guide their expected free energy
calculations, let's say.
What is there something critical to
experience per se which makes it
adaptive
um for these
free energy minimizing systems and their
meta-cognitive capacities to track their
ability to minimize free energy?
Yes, I believe that there is. Before I
um
explain why,
I just want to flag maybe for later
discussion uh
so I don't I don't divert us from the
question that you're the line of
questioning that you're currently
following. But I'm not so sure that I
would describe the mechanism that um
I just articulated as a meta-cognitive
uh mechanism. I think there's a
difference between um the feeling um and
what the feeling's about. In other
words, there's a difference between uh
the the the
the raw feeling, which is the
registering of what's happening to your
in the in the terms that you were just
using uh to your free energy and um
you're cognizing uh representing uh to
use another language um
what uh
in in the context within which I'm
feeling this, uh what is causing me to
feel this. So Sure. I Yeah, I certainly
I certainly agree with that. Yeah. I
didn't mean to say in terms of
meta-cognitive purely this notion that
it can be done in some pre-reflexive,
non-conceptual, non-representational
manner.
Purely this notion that
there is at least embedded in phenomenal
space some self-referential It could be
very low level like lived experience I
am doing well, I am doing badly. But it
doesn't have to be a higher order
narrative
um I'm doing well, I'm doing badly.
Okay, good. Now um to your question. You
ask why can't this function that I've
just described uh as the mechanism of
feeling, uh you're asking why can't it
go on in the dark? Uh why why why is it
why is it necessary for it to be felt?
So let me if you'll just bear with me
for a for a couple of minutes, let me
unpack the mechanism uh in in in
slightly more pedantic detail. Um we're
talking about a self-organizing system
uh which is is which is intrinsically
imbued uh with the
um
the the the um
function that it must continue what it
does must uh
maximize its chances of continuing to
exist. So that's a a sort of
pre a
a that's a starting point of of
any complex dynamical free
self-organizing system.
So
there is a kind of intrinsic I don't say
kind of. There is an intrinsic
intentionality in such a system. It's
trying to achieve something. I don't
mean it's meta-cognitively trying to
achieve something. I just mean it has it
has a goal directedness. Uh let me let
me put it that way.
Um now it's I then said that um
the monitoring of how well or badly I'm
doing, uh this this can this valence
function um that's what valence is
because it's just to the extent that
what I'm doing um is moving me out of my
viable bounds, is making me less likely
to survive to and vice versa, you know,
when it's moving me back towards my
viable bounds. That just is good or bad
for the system. Uh
the but again, I need to emphasize the
point that I emphasized earlier. It just
is good or bad for the system.
In in in uh Nagel's sense, it's it's
it's good for the system and good to the
system, you know, so it's it's not good
or bad
in any
objective sense. It's good or bad only
in a subjective sense. Now you're saying
why can't that sort of monitoring uh be
done um in the dark? I'm saying it can.
That's why I made the point earlier
about the difference between the
continuous variable of total need or
total free energy um and the categorical
variable um of which which need am I
talking about here? Categorical
variables just are distinguished
qualitatively. As I said earlier, thirst
and sleepiness just are not the same
thing. Uh so they are categorical
variables. Uh that means they're
qualitatively different. So what I've
just described
is something which mechanistically
is a felt state. I'm saying I'm saying
from the point of view of the system,
there is an
an existential
uh variable uh called valence. In other
words, this this is
uh good or bad for me uh for my
continued existence whether or not this
is meta-cognitively reflected, it
doesn't matter. There is this thing
which just is good or bad and just is
subjective. And it just is qualitatively
differentiated. So if you're saying that
there's a certain function uh that the
system has uh which is intrinsically
subjective, intrinsically valenced, um
and intrinsically qualitatively
distinguished. I'm saying that is a
feeling. So if you say how can that go
on in the dark, I would say what do you
mean? Uh
this intrinsically is something that is
felt. That's the a mechanistic
description of what a feeling is. And I
think that the crucial step um that
uh needs to be um
identified there
um is that is it justifiable to take the
point of view of the system? In other
words, what is it that justifies one uh
taking the viewpoint of the system? And
I I hope you can see in what I said uh
uh the in the intrinsically subjective
nature of the things that I was talking
about there. That justifies us The
selfhood of the system justifies us in
taking the subjective point of view of
the system. And if you do that, from a
subjective point of view, the mechanism
I've just described um
just is a feeling. That's what we mean
by a feeling. So um I I I I hope I've
been plain and clear enough.
You have you have been for me. I mean,
I'm familiar with these arguments of
sort of intrinsic intentionality. I
mean, as you know, they go all the way
back to Heidegger and this notion of
taking a stance on your own being and
the idea that it's kind of open-ended we
are naturally, as you say, directed
towards this kind of open-ended
futurity.
And I that gets fleshed out in Yeah,
I've recently just finished Evan
Thompson's Mind in Life and he is
wonderfully clear on that about the this
idea of kind of we sense make, we the
Umwelt comes out of our own stance that
we take upon the world. I guess I still
have a kind of residual Chalmers
skepticism
which is
does
and I think therefore it's necessary to
get kind of clear on the axioms that
you're taking here.
Does
taking an intentional stance on your own
being require consciousness? Maybe
intentional Well, intentional's actually
not necessarily the wrong word here.
But I mean, can you have a
self-organizing complex dynamical
system? And I I think there's an
interesting point here about the
imperative, but I'll come back to that.
But can you have a complex self
organizing system
which is autopoietic in the sense it it
is intended towards its own
self-persistence
which need not be conscious or at least
conscious in the way that we think of a
conscious as subjectively conscious. I
can almost imagine that you have a
non-subjective
consciousness
I an an objective consciousness if one
could imagine such a thing, which might
in some ways
uh suit that self-organizing process
because it gets rid of
bias and
uh over-fitting your data and
confirmation bias and all this other
stuff. I recognize we've gone slightly
off the beaten track here, but I'm just
wondering whether there's
like one thing that I'm missing. Maybe
it's an axiom or maybe it's an argument,
I'm not sure, about exactly why
autopoietic self-organization entails
subjectivity per se.
Um well, let me start um
with an appeal to authority, which is
not a good thing. Uh and then uh let me
add a um semantic point, which is not a
good thing. And then I'll I'll answer
your question properly. Sure. The appeal
to authority, I have to say um
I was very pleased that Tom Nagel uh
Mhm. wrote a commentary on my book uh in
the journal
Yeah, he wrote it in the Journal of
Consciousness Studies.
Um
and there he's he said in uh in in
relation to exactly the question you've
just asked that he thinks that it's a
it's it's a non-start non-starter uh the
idea of an affective zombie. So, he
accepts that
Mhm. there cannot be an affective
zombie. Uh this this is a this is a non
sequitur.
Um but that's that's an appeal to
authority. I'm just saying no less uh
a person uh That's an appeal to
authority. to the nature of
subjectivity, uh he he says he he
accepts that there cannot be an an
affective zombie. In other words, there
cannot be uh a system equipped with the
functionality that I've just described
that is a zombie because if it were a
zombie, it wouldn't have the
functionality I've described. But that's
just an appeal to authority. Then
there's the semantic point. Um
I want to make clear that I'm talking
about feeling. Okay? And you asked me
earlier about affect and you said
different people use the word in
different ways and they mean different
things by it. Um
I hope from my description of how what I
mean by the word, you can see why I use
it synonymously with feeling. Um Yeah. I
like to use the word feeling when I'm
discussing the issues that you're
raising because
it just is an oxymoron to speak of a
feeling that you don't feel. Uh there's
there
it's not a feeling if you don't feel it.
Uh and and so the thing denoted by that
word um is the thing I'm talking about.
Mhm. uh already that I accept that
that's just a semantic point and you
know but it it it leads to something
more than a semantic point. When I say
the thing I'm talking about is the thing
denoted by the word feeling therefore
that thing I'm talking about cannot be
unfelt uh because uh that's the thing
I'm talking about. Uh the thing I'm
talking about is the thing that we call
feeling. Now, that leads me to the
substantive answer to your question. I
really do believe
that this this question uh as you
formulated it um I I I recognize of
course as you formulated it derived from
or with um with
reference to David Chalmers' formulation
of it.
Um
I don't think this question would ever
have arisen if it wasn't for the fact
that uh we were using as a at the time
that Chalmers wrote his famous paper and
the book that followed it
um and formulated this term the hard
problem of consciousness um we were
using as our model example of
consciousness visual consciousness.
Uh
um this was um perhaps
uh inevitable because consciousness is
dominated by vision uh and uh it was
perhaps um because Francis Crick used it
as his model example in his book
the the the
uh what was it called? The Astonishing
Hypothesis, which came out 1 year before
uh Chalmers' paper.
Um the thing is that I think that was
the wrong place to start. That all of
those questions arise only because
vision is not an intrinsically conscious
function. Uh
even the highest of visual um
functionality uh in other words uniquely
human cortical um visual functions like
reading with comprehension can be done
without consciousness.
So the question why doesn't all this
information processing go on in the dark
without any inner feel, which is to
quote exactly the the physiology that
Chalmers used.
I think that that's a legitimate
question and I can see why the
puzzlement arises because you can do
exactly the same thing without
consciousness. So, you know reading with
comprehension, why on earth do you ever
why does there have to be something it
is like to read if the exact same thing
can be done without there being
something it's like to do it. Now you
then once you've got this puzzlement
then somebody like you, a reader of
Chalmers, comes to my argument and says
well, why is it inconceivable that this
thing couldn't be done by an affective
zombie? And I'm saying, well, that's a
silly question because look at what I've
just told you. You know I've told you
what the function is. Uh I've told you
that it is in intrinsically subjective,
it's intrinsically existential, it's
intrinsically valence uh and it's
qualitatively distinguished and if you
describe such a mechanism uh it uh which
is necessarily registered by the system
then you're describing a feeling. So,
what do you mean uh it could be not
felt? Uh it wouldn't be a feeling if it
was not felt and I've told you what the
feeling does. You know um uh I guess I
guess I need to be a bit a little bit
more philosophically robust here and
it's come to mind here that one can take
Chalmers' claims claims and and that '95
paper and the book in multiple ways. So,
one is
why um couldn't this functionality be
done in the dark?
And I take and I agree actually that
feeling
a priori in and of itself by definition
has to be felt. So, that's something
that you can have
which needs to be felt. So, that that
notion of in the darkness
doesn't really stand when it comes to uh
affect.
And another the other part of David
Chalmers' argument is
how do neural processes give rise to
subjective states?
To what it feels like to be me or you.
And I guess
that is a different direction which I
presume you probably don't think there
is an answer to. And I guess what that
leads me back to is when I'm talking
about this in first-person consciousness
sure feeling gets us there.
I guess what I was saying is
if we go if we have this sort of view
from nowhere, we can go back all the way
to the uh evolutionary start
and let's say we did start as
non-conscious beings. Why was it
functionally adaptive for human beings
to develop feelings in the first place?
Where's
if this metacognitive
non-representational
uh self-referential process
what became imbued with feeling
w- I'm not going to ask how that
happened because no one knows.
But I guess the question here is why did
that happen?
And that's when I say, well, couldn't
couldn't it have happened in the dark?
Sure, feelings themselves can't happen
in the dark per se.
But the function that feelings fulfill,
namely this monitoring process why why
did that have to evolve so as to contain
qualia, subjectivity and and so on.
That's the kind of crux of the question,
I guess.
Um I think you're I think either you're
asking three questions or I've got three
answers uh
to your question. So, I'm so I'm not So,
okay, so I don't Okay, I'm going to lose
I think there's only one here. One is
Okay, so I'm not fussed about how. I'm
going to lose my train of thought. I'm
an old guy. Go go go go go go go,
please. So, let me let me Go go go. So
um if I haven't already lost it um Ah.
Yeah, what I want to say first of all is
the um
Mary uh the visual neuroscientist Yeah.
um
if if if she were an affective
uh if she were to describe the to know
everything there is to know uh about the
mechanism of feeling uh it would
necessarily predict that it feels like
something. Uh and and she would know
something about what it is like to have
a feeling from the mechanistic account
of it.
Um that's that's that's the first thing
that you were saying in your question
brought that answer to my mind. But I
think you said you concede that point.
Uh I I'm uninterested. I'm uninterested.
I Well, now I'm interested, but I was
uninterested in the how.
And I'm and I'll give you the feelings
need I guess my question is
evolutionarily w-
does the function of feeling need to be
felt? Yes. So, um that leads to or that
to get to that, I've got to go via a
second thing that I I heard you say
uh which is um you know, how does the
physiological process cause the
subjective feeling state? And there I
have to make clear that I am a dual
aspect monist. Um
I'm You may want to explain what that is
for the audience. Yes, I I will. Um
the I'll put it uh uh very simply. Uh
when I wake up in the morning uh
before I open my eyes uh I experience my
existence, I think to myself I am Mark
Solms uh thank God I'm still alive.
That's my mind.
Okay? Mhm. Uh then I stagger over to the
bathroom and I look in the mirror um and
I see this body uh uh
called Mark Solms and I say uh there is
further evidence that I still exist,
thank God. Uh now please note both of
those things I'm calling them Mark
Solms. Uh in other words, these are two
um
two phenomenal uh two appearances, two
observational perspectives uh upon one
and the same thing. So, there is the
subjective being of Mark Solms that I
experience mentally when I wake up
before I open my eyes and then there is
the objective bodily
uh thing called Mark Solms that I
experience visually when I look at him
in the mirror. Uh
that's the dual aspect monism says these
are not two different things, not two
different ontological entities. There's
one underlying ontological entity and
that's called Mark Solms. So, then the
question is which is an abstraction.
Then then the question becomes well,
what stuff is Mark Solms made of? Uh and
I'm saying Mark Solms is made of a
functional mechanism uh
and which the one I was describing
earlier
is a self-organizing therefore
in biological terms a homeostatic
system. Uh homeostasis is a mechanism.
It's an abstraction. There's there's
there's we infer the underlying
mechanisms
from the the the observed data. Uh when
it comes to
the the apparatus
of the mind, the thing that we are
talking about here, which is also the
apparatus of the brain, it's that
apparatus that we are talking about.
It's the it's the the functional
principles governing this part of nature
that we infer from the two observables.
So,
when it comes to um
for example, memory, you know, you can
have a memory, that's the experience of
a memory,
or you can see optogenetically the
neurons that are activated
whilst you are having that same memory.
These are two perspectives upon one
thing, which is an abstraction called
the memory system or the function of
memory. So,
I think that that is the actual thing
that we are studying in cognitive
neuroscience.
Although, I don't like to call it
cognitive neuroscience cuz that seems to
exclude affective neuroscience. So, the
thing the thing that we are studying in
what we are let's call it
neuropsychology, which is a slightly
less prejudiced word. Um
in this in this mind and brain science,
I think that the the
um
the the ultimate object of study of
neuropsychology is things like the
memory system,
uh the perceptual system, uh the
executive system, and so on. We're
trying to discern the laws,
the underlying monistic laws
governing this part of nature that we
can observe from these two different
perspectives, both both the objective
and the subjective one. Now, um
sorry if I if I'm getting quite
abstract. No, no, no. No, it's very
useful.
To come back to the essential point, um
if that is the
framework the metaphysical framework
within which I'm working and we all have
to when it comes to the mind-body
relation,
we have to adopt a metaphysical
framework and it's good that we are
clear about which one we're adopting.
That's the one I'm adopting. Within that
framework, it doesn't make any sense to
say how did the physiological phenomenon
cause the psychological phenomenon. They
are those two phenomena are dual
manifestations of a single underlying
cause. That underlying cause is the
mechanism that I spoke of earlier, which
explains them both.
Um
the free energy principle is is is is
such a such a thing. It's it's a it's a
a principle which governs both how we
feel
and what brain arousal mechanisms
we observe physiologically. In other
words, what you see with your eyes and
what you feel with your feelings are
both manifestations of that single
underlying mechanism. So, to say how
does the brain process cause the feeling
is to ask the wrong question. It's to
ask a question that assumes a
metaphysical relationship, which I think
is the wrong assumption. It's like
saying if I look with my eyes, I see a
flash of lightning. Um if I listen with
my ears, I hear a clap of thunder.
And I ask the question how does that
visual thing the flash of lightning
cause that auditory thing, the clap of
thunder. It's to misunderstand that
they're actually both caused
by a
geoelectrical event, which we describe
abstractly using the the laws of
physics, using the language of physics
or or
or um
ultimate forces, you know, that that
that kind of language. It's not
something that you observe. It's the
mechanism that you the thing that you
infer that underlies it.
So, um
when you're saying you're wanting to
know how, I'm saying I have answered you
how when I described to you what the
mechanism is
and I very importantly, I need to make
this clear.
The mechanism I described to you, the
mechanism of feeling that is, um which
is
which which you can observe from two
observational perspectives. In other
words, you can observe brain arousal
processes and you can observe
subjectively feelings
that these are both manifestations of a
single mechanism. That's the one that I
described to you and this is the
important I said very importantly. It
also explains why this mechanism has two
um
perceptual surfaces. Why why it has two
perceptual perspectives. It explains why
such a mechanism has a subjective
perspective because not everything
everything geometrically has a has a
subjective perspective. In other words,
you can say there is there is such a
thing as
the perspective of being a cup or being
a table, but that doesn't mean that
there is something it is like to be a
cup or to be a table. So, I'm saying the
mechanism I've described um which is
which is a mechanism which does not
exist does not explain the behavior of
cups and tables
is why there is nothing it is like to be
a cup or a table. So,
remember that the underlying monistic
ontological
entity that we are studying is that
mechanism which which which we can study
both objectively and subjectively and
I've described why this
particular mechanism has a subjective
aspect. Now, to come to what I
understood to be the third part of or
third uh
aspect of your question.
Um which is a a sort of an evolutionary
question. You're saying why did this
happen? What functionality is added?
What why what is gained by this that
that couldn't go on in the dark. I've
already explained why I believe that
mechanism can't go on in the dark. Now,
I want to explain what what it adds.
It is
in fact, I have in a way already
explained it, but let me articulate it
in a slightly different way.
Um a organism, let's say an organism
because we're talking about living
things here, but it's there's another
question as to whether they necessarily
have to be living things, but we could
say a system, but let's just say a
biological system, an organism. Um which
has needs.
In other words, it has its own
um
biologically viable states and it has to
remain within those states. In other
words, it's a an organism which
functions homeostatically.
It it it needs predictions as to how to
satisfy those needs. In other words, how
to how to return to homeostasis when
it's deviating from it. And we are born
with such predictions. Us living things
have innate predictions. Those are
called reflexes.
Those precisely are our autonomic
functions. So,
um
I have a I have a constant um
need to balance my blood gases. There's
a there's a balance between oxygen and
carbon dioxide that's viable for a human
being. And I have a very simple way of
meeting that need, which is that I
breathe automatically. Um my my
intercostal muscles expand expand my
diaphragm, that sucks in oxygen.
And then
the the the the the relaxing of that of
those muscles and that
expels carbon dioxide. And there is
actually a need detector in your
hypothalamus if you want to describe
this mechanism anatomically, which is
constantly monitoring oxygen carbon
dioxide oxygen carbon dioxide. But
there's one prediction as to how to how
to
how to maintain the viable balance and
that is this autonomic breathing
mechanism. Now, why do we ever become
conscious of our need to breathe? I know
you are now becoming conscious of it
because I'm talking about it. Normally,
you're not conscious of it. Um
Hm. In other words, what is added by
becoming conscious of it? So, imagine
an an organism equipped with the with
the need I've just described and with
the reflexive prediction, the innate
prediction, the fixed innate instinctual
prediction as to how to meet that need.
That's fine until you place such an
organism in an unpredicted environment.
In other words, something not predicted
by natural selection. In other words,
not the default environment for which
this prediction is an appropriate one,
the the one that you should just breathe
at a regular rate. In other words, for
example, what happens if you're in a
carbon dioxide filled room? Uh You're no
longer in the usual
default environment. You're in a burning
building
and the room is full of carbon dioxide.
At that point, you become conscious of
your need to breathe.
This is the why question that you're
asking. Why
do you become conscious of your need to
breathe? It's because now you're in a
state of uncertainty as to what to do.
Your reflex autonomic prediction doesn't
cut it. So, you
behave stochastically. You're
in a state of distress.
You're
You're suffering
a
suffocation alarm
or
respiratory distress or air hunger. It
goes by various names. And why it comes
to consciousness as a feeling is because
as you randomly go upstairs trying to
do something other than your
instinctual, your normal reflexive
action, it feels worse.
And so, that was the wrong decision. It
was a bad choice to go upstairs and and
the and the organism registers it in the
form of this feeling of suffocation is
getting worse. So, you change your mind
and you go downstairs instead and there
you get the enormous relief of feeling
better, you know, being able to being
able to breathe the oxygen. So, that
that feeling
has guided your voluntary action. In
fact, has has has made possible what we
call voluntary action. It's not just
random behavior because
the your your existing prediction
doesn't cut it. What you do is, as I
said earlier, predictive work in
progress. In other words, you actually
feel your way through the problem and
and and come up with the new prediction
which you then lay down. That is the
adaptive advantage. That is what is
evolutionarily added by this extended
form of homeostasis in which you don't
just have some sort of automatic
regulator of
that that that keeps you within your
viable bounds. You have in addition to
those automatic regulators, you have a
further mechanism which kicks in when
the automatic regulator isn't working
because you're not in the environment
that it it expects.
And it it enables you to
to navigate that that novel unpredicted
uncertain environment.
It's one of the What I've just said one
of the reasons why I say that that that
consciousness is felt uncertainty.
That's
That's a
pithy way of describing what it actually
is. But I hope that I've answered your
question there by saying what it adds.
It adds It adds the
the the the ability to survive in
unpredicted novel environments. Prior to
the
evolution of this
mechanism, this extended form of
homeostasis, this this subjective form
of
extension of homeostasis, what would
have happened
is that
if you have a population
of the organisms that the hypothetical
organisms I'm talking about, they all
have this stereotyped fixed prediction
as to what to do. If they find
themselves in a novel situation because
of the innate variation in the genome,
some of them will do the right thing
and some of them will do the wrong thing
in their in their random sort of
thrashing about. The few that do the
right thing
will then pass on
that
adaptation to the next generation. In
other words, the next generation when
they find themselves in this what was
previously a novel situation, it will
not be a novel situation for the next
generation. The The functionality that
I've described supersedes that. That is
the mechanism of natural selection
whereby over generations
the predictions are improved by natural
selection. The functionality I've
described enables the organism within
its own lifetime to improve its
predictive model
in in in radically uncertain
circumstances.
And thereby to survive and reproduce.
There's a lot there.
So, I want to start by being
philosophically skeptical and therefore
annoying
and say that I still think that this is
resting on an axiom that for example,
consciousness is there for
unpredictability.
Because
I still can't see why in principle
natural selection couldn't endowed us
with just a very good
monitor
of what to do
in uncertain circumstances. So,
I
I can't imagine why a zombie a
philosophical zombie wouldn't be able to
recognize as I go up the stairs
there's more smoke, it's getting worse.
Oh, let me go downstairs, right? And
this is just you can just keep fleshing
out and having recursive iterations on
the mechanism before it needs to come
on.
And come online that is.
And so, the way that I thought about it
just to sort of put my cards on the
table because I've been acting cryptic,
is I wonder whether
I wonder whether
consciousness acts as a coarse-grained
representation allows for speed and
manageable data
and
in
ingenders manageable data compression
such that we cannot
we can't in principle
attend to every single data
sources out there in the world.
But what consciousness allows us to do
is to compress the data that is in the
world into something one that's
prioritized and two that can be acted
upon in the fast manner.
Whether this is predictable or
unpredictable circumstances. I don't
think it will need to be done in
unpredictable circumstances.
But the pure notion that consciousness
is unpredictable is is there for
unpredictable circumstances, I don't
think can skirt the problem or the
contention that
hypothetic we can never run the
counterfactual.
But there is a there is a hypothetical
counterfactual where all of this is
being done offline you just have a very
adaptive sensor in the hypothalamus,
let's say, who doesn't who doesn't need
an online self model
to any signal in some phenomenal way.
So, that's that again, I don't feel we
need to go down this rabbit hole. Um
Well, well,
you have articulated your view. I will
just say something very briefly about it
which is that
that is in in
in essence and I'm I'm sorry to be so
reductive about the subtleties in what
you've just said. But it is in essence a
attentional mechanism that you've
described. And
I'm saying that's fine. I spoke earlier
about prioritization. So, that's that's
built into what I'm saying. But
it's not just any old attentional
mechanism. It's attention to my
homeostatic state. In other words, to my
deviation from my viable bounds. It's
not attention to anything in the world.
In other words,
just unpredictability. I'm saying no,
it's not just unpredictability. It's
unpredictability as to how to satisfy
this need. In other words, it's a
certain kind of unpredictability for a
certain kind of system. I think that
that is the ground zero of feeling. That
is how it comes into existence. So, it
is by the mechanism you described, but
only applied to a particular part of
nature not not to everything in the
universe. That's That's very useful.
I've actually just written this paper
with the help of Carl and Lance LaCosta
about sort of
eliding the endogenous exogenous
attention distinction within active
inference by saying that attention is
basically as as we've been speaking
about a priority filter, but always for
the sense-making organism.
And and and in active inference, you can
say well, and then you flesh that out
and say well, the deepest most precise
preferences are encoded at the deepest
level of the generative hierarchy, hence
why
I don't care where my phone is when I'm
suffocating for example because the
preference I have my phone is far less
precise and far higher than um That is
exactly how I see it. Yep. Yeah. Okay.
So,
So, I wanted to ask You said something
about So, we have dual aspect monism
that we can describe two phenomena. We I
can take two perspectives on
a phenomenon like memory for example. We
can think of the hippocampus and we can
also think of what it is like to have a
memory. And you said that what the the
real target of cognitive neuroscience or
neuropsychology should be is the single
mechanism that underlies both of those
perspectives and you preferred that
active inference or the free energy
principle might be one of those
mechanisms.
I wonder whether this was relating to
what people talk about in term in active
inference as a dual information
geometry.
And what that is is
for the audience and
I spoke to Vanya Visser about this
actually yesterday, so the podcast
should be out before this one. So,
people can go there. But the idea is
that we have an intrinsic geometry which
looks at how the actual internal states
of the Markov blanket evolve over time
and then we have the extrinsic geometry
which is
what how they are
uh
manifesting variational beliefs about
the external states. And one is kind of
one you can kind of view as if you
wanted to take a metaphysical stance or
a phenomenal stance, one is the view
from within and one is the view from
without. I wonder whether that dual
aspect fits quite nicely onto your dual
aspect monism, or whether you thought
about that.
Yes,
what you're saying intuitively appeals
to me. Uh
when you say have you
I thought about it enough for precisely
10 seconds, and it
intuitively appeals to me.
There's a paper called
Markovian monism,
which is by Van der and Carl. So, that
that that's where this is. Yes.
I I just wonder, you know, I spoke to
Van der about this yesterday, and I
said, "What are the metaphysical
consequences of this?" Before we move
on, may I just say there's something
about
the
there's something about cuz now I'm
remembering that paper. Um and I'm
remembering what I thought when I read
it. I think that there is something
special about
precision optimization in relation to
what you're talking about.
In that the precision
assigned to the incoming error signal
in relation to the outgoing prediction
is assigned by the system
to those to those
to that message passing, as it were. So,
I think that there's there's a special
place
for precision optimization in in the
story that you just described there.
Yeah, absolutely. Yeah, I mean, in terms
of the paper that I just wrote, that's
exactly it. It in terms of the more like
in terms of a technical base graph POMDP
scheme, what we're saying here is that
sort of higher order preferences
govern precision weighting over what's
called the likelihood matrix, the A
matrix. And that's kind of been, you
know, Feldman and Friston and then later
papers have proposed that that really is
what attention is. It's optimizing that
precision weighting. Yes. And that means
that we're not Yeah.
No, please go ahead.
Only to add that I think a really
critical point that I really want to
stress in that paper is that that's not
just precision per se. So, precision I
take to be a very
strict mathematical construct in
inverse entropy or inverse covariance,
whatever you want to say.
But not all signals which are given
gain, you know, extra gain, synaptic
gain, or given attention are only those
which are precise, i.e., which have a
clear cause.
Rather, we
govern our attention is governed
fundamentally by our goals, even if that
the object of attention isn't
necessarily precise, right? It can be
very ambiguous, but it's very important
that I pay attention to whether my
garden hose is a garden hose or a snake.
And that will also be affected for
whether I'm in London or whether I'm in
Sydney. So, just to add that I think
people it's really important to
distinguish attention, precision, and
precision weighting as three individual
constructs. Yes.
That makes good sense to me.
Good. I'm So,
I'll put it in the in more sort of
everyday terms.
We
that that um
It has to do cuz remember I was saying
it's a particular type of system, and
that's another way of saying
what you're saying. That
if things
with respect to the precision over my
policies, if things are turning out as
expected, that's good. If uncertainty
prevails, that's bad. And so, you know,
this is why it is good to have
confidence in your
in your policies
because it will result in good feelings.
Absolutely.
Go ahead. No, but I gathered that you
wanted to move on to another topic.
Well, yeah, I mean, actually just in
reference I I like making sure that
people know I kind of feel like I should
let people know where they can go to
read all this stuff. So, just in terms
of the precision over your policies,
this is known as the gamma parameter in
active inference. And if people want to
read about that, Casper Hesp's 201 2021
paper is a really good place to start,
where he talks about valence in terms of
this gamma precision. Okay.
Yes. I So, I I um I watched your two
conversations with Lisa Feldman Barrett
and greatly enjoyed them.
And I really Yeah, I thought they were
really fascinating and a very novel way
of doing scientific discussion, cuz
normally it's very angry and on Twitter.
Um
I thought a really interesting tough
thing that came up, although it was only
really briefly touched upon,
was kind of the distinction between
interoception and exteroception.
And I I found I actually I've never
really thought that it could potentially
be quite a blurry line.
But I thought that Lisa was
keen to say that some of the things that
you were proposing were fundamentally
exteroceptive, i.e., a pinprick or
something like that, could also be
construed as interoceptive.
So, if we say, okay, let's take the
pinprick example,
and let's talk about affect. So, you're
not I if I'm say that if I'm correct,
you wouldn't believe that all affects is
fundamentally interoceptive. Is that a
fair play fair thing to say? Oh, yes. I
absolutely disagree with that view, but
slightly comically in relation to the
discussion with Lisa Feldman Barrett
that you're referring to. That was the
starting point of that discussion was
that I said I disagree with her and Anil
Seth in their in their associating
affect with interoception. For them,
interoception is affect, and
exteroception is this other form of
perception. Remember, to them, affect is
just a modality of perception. It's an
interoceptive modality of perception.
And I was saying, "No, I don't agree
with that at all. I don't think that it
is." And then I used the example of
pain, and I said, "What could be more
exteroceptive, you know, than this thing
is from the outside being stuck into my
finger?" Or a fright, you know, there's
something happens out there in the
world, and that thing out there in the
world startles me. So, it's
exteroceptive.
And so, I was saying affect
clearly is not exteroceptive. Then she
got into these gymnastics that you're
referring to saying, "Well, you know, if
you do this, then
a pinprick is interoceptive." And I
said, "Well, fine. You know, if you do
this, then
that's fine. But to me, the crucial
thing is
that it that it's neither the
exteroceptive stimulus nor the
interoceptive stimulus that is felt. In
other words, I don't believe the feeling
is the perception. I believe that the
feeling is the homeostatic deviation.
Homeostats are not They are not
interoceptive or exteroceptive. They're
both. They are registering a
a configuration
which it which it infers this
this is bad for me or this is good in
relation to the particular category of
need that we're talking about. So, So, I
don't think you and Lisa would
necessarily disagree on that if I
listened to that conversation correctly,
because I think she was keen, and I
guess it's a fundamental part of her
theory, that there isn't there isn't
necessarily meaning in the data signal
itself, and it's only in its
collision with the prediction that we
get in Bayesian terms a posterior, which
relates to our actual fundamental prior,
and that divergence is what you might
call affect. So, I can see you would
disagree on that. In terms of this Can I
just make clear there, because, you
know, these disagreements with Lisa
I think are very important
for the future of our field.
By which I mean I mean affect of
science. That's the field I'm talking
about. That's the that's what I share
with Lisa is an interest in the in the
fundamental nature of affect, or what
she calls emotion, because,
as you said at the beginning,
affect and emotion and and so on, these
words are used differently by different
people. For her, affect does not have
quality. It has valence and arousal, but
it is not categorically
distinguishable
in in its in its intrinsic nature.
Um so, um the you're quite right in
everything you just said there, that she
and I don't differ in the things that
you just said there. But for me, the
crucial point, and you can see in
relation to everything that I've said to
you already, why it's crucial,
is that I think that the starting point
is that those homeostats are innate. You
know, that we are born with
categorically distinct homeostats.
Um and the
I won't repeat everything I said
earlier, but it is from those homeostats
that the
ultimately that the that the that the
quality of feeling arises. When I was
saying thirst feels different from
hunger and so on. And remember, I'm
saying these are not only interoceptive.
Fright
feels different from pain. These are
exteroceptive. Pain to me, pretty
obviously, when you stick something in
from the outside, it's exteroceptive.
It's part of the somatosensory system,
you know, this is one of the classical
exteroceptive senses.
Um
So, the homeostat um the detection of
this particular pattern of exteroceptive
and interoceptive
signals um
this
is a deviation from this category of
need. And if you prioritize that
deviation, in other words, this is the
one that I'm going to now
I'm going to my
This is the most salient category of
need. This is the one where my I'm going
to palpate my uncertainty as I act in
the world. This is, in other words, the
one that I'm going to that is now going
to govern my voluntary behavior.
That the quality of the feeling that
governs
that action cycle
is going to arise from the category
of need that we're talking about. In
other words, from the homeostat. Her
view is that there are no innate
categories of emotion. And I've just
explained why I don't agree with that.
That's I think is the fundamental
difference between her and me.
That's what I felt was the That's what I
felt was the fundamental difference. And
just so I can get clarity for myself,
is your view that there is a strict
mapping, at least numerically, between
the number of homeostats and the number
of basic categories?
So, is there a homeostat for Well, these
are the Pankseppian basic emotion, you
know, is there a homeostat for
seeking? Is there a homeostat for rage
or lust or whatever?
I do believe that there's a a homeostat
for each one of those what he calls
basic emotions. Um but I need to make
clear that those what he calls basic
emotions
are not the
sum total of the basic homeostatic need
mechanisms that are at work in the in
the human
or mammalian or, for that matter,
vertebrate organism.
The the the
Many of the things that we spoke about
at the beginning of our conversation,
things like hunger and thirst and
and
respiratory
feelings and so on, these are not
emotions. These are at least that they
don't feature in Panksepp's taxonomy of
the emotions because for him emotions
are not these things. He calls them
bodily affects.
So, there are many
homeostats, not seven. There are many
many many many many homeostats in the
human organism. And it's a very telling
fact that not all of them give rise to
feelings, like blood pressure
regulation, for example. There's no
feeling of, you know, how well or badly
you're doing in terms of
in terms of um
regulating your blood pressure.
And
I'm just using one example. There are
many such examples. There There are ones
which are transitional, which are
normally run autonomically, and
sometimes we feel them. And I just gave
an example of that when I spoke about
respiration. That normally it's it's
it's handled
autonomically, but then under certain
circumstances it comes to consciousness.
So,
I'm sorry. I'm probably being
overly
pedantic, but the my point is yes, I do
agree with you that there for for each
need there's a homeostat, but there more
than seven of them. There are many many
many more than seven of them. And um
only some of them ever come to
consciousness, and only some of them
might be called emotions in my way of
using the word emotion. But here's the
further a very important point. Um
the fact that they are categorical needs
doesn't mean that they aren't amalgams
of them.
It doesn't mean that they also aren't
higher order metacognitive
amalgams and elaborations and so on.
For her for for Lisa, that's the
starting point. The starting point is
that they are these learned categories
that we then
they are what she calls emotion
concepts, which we then apply to
to what we
experience perceptually. And I'm saying,
"Yeah, of course there are these learned
concepts,
but they start with innate concepts.
Those are Those are the Those are the
the homeostats that I'm talking about."
How we come to regulate through
allostasis
and and and and learning
all of these different mechanisms
and orchestrate them all with each other
and so on, especially us human beings
with all of these higher order abstract
concepts that we use to do so,
it includes everything that she writes
about. I think that what she writes
about
describes something that definitely does
happen, but I just
I just question the
the assumption that there are no innate
categories to begin with. It It just
makes no evolutionary sense and makes no
physiological sense. It just doesn't map
onto what we know about how the brain
works. That's That's the That's the
point I wanted to make.
Yes, that was the That was the big
sticking point. And there was this kind
of back and forth about what evidence
is, which we don't we don't necessarily
need to go into. But people can watch
it, and I thought it was very
interesting. Well, when when if if you
do if you, dear listener or viewer, do
watch it, I want you to to notice one
thing which I thought was was was
especially important. Um it's that
because Lisa's starting point is that
this idea that there are particular
circuits for particular emotions and so
on, which which of course can be
parodied and can be caricatured and can
be made to look like an idiotic
localizationist stupid idea.
But but when she says there are no such
systems, there are no innate brain
systems for innate emotions and and and
other
categories of organismic organismic
need,
when she says that, please note in this
conversation with me,
I learned that she says the same of
vision as opposed to somatic sensation
as opposed to olfaction. She says these
two are not innate systems.
So, if that's what she means, if if her
if her
um
way of understanding what we mean by an
innate system,
her way of of of using that terminology
excludes
the usefulness of speaking about a
visual system, which we all have, and an
auditory system that we all have, and so
on. I think you need to understand that
it's in that way that she's questioning
whether there are basic emotional
systems in the brain. If if if if it's
such a radical claim that she's that
she's making that
we should not speak of any innate
systems
of the kind that we do when we speak of
a visual and auditory and somatic
sensory and so on system.
If if emotion is being lumped in with
that claim, then it's not a claim only
about emotion. It's a whole different
way of thinking about what are useful
concepts. And her reasoning for saying
there's no innate visual system is that
if you're blind, your visual system will
be
you know, will serve different
functions,
not innately visual. Well, of course, if
you're blind, it's going to go in an
anomalous It's going to organize in an
anomalous way, but that doesn't mean
that it's not useful in biology to speak
of
the fact that in the normal state of
things there is an an innate visual
system.
But
Yes. I wonder whether I could, you know,
Lisa's not here to state her piece, and
so people should go and listen. And I'd
love to have her on. Um
I'm wondering whether I can sort of
steel man
and well, actually not steel man either
yourself or her, but also potentially
I'll, you know, offer a middle
suggestion, which is
could we perhaps propose rather than
Well, I wonder whether Lisa would say
she might disagree that there are innate
concepts. Would she disagree that there
are innate processes?
And by that I mean I can take a sort of
active inference biological active
inference stance on this, that there are
functions and anatomical systems in the
body and brain
which have priors to self-organize in a
certain way. And this is the work of
Mike Levin and Frans de Waal and this
kind of work about morphospace and how
that flashes out. And so I wonder
whether
because I personally and I think this is
an argument that goes all the way back
to Jerry Fodor
and the debates around Chomsky and and
innate language, I can't see how, for
example,
fear
would even get ever get off the ground
with no
innate priming for fear. Right? Like I
agree,
fear then becomes socially modulated,
but how would that categorization, like
I don't think Lisa would deny that for
you and I as fully fleshed conscious
propositional using like language users,
we can think about fear and have it as a
concrete object. But how that ever gets
off the ground in terms of what makes
something fear, what makes something
first without some uh something guiding
that process, whether it's just a
singular concept that acts as a template
which things get fit fit into, or
process
uh like let's say an innate inductive in
process, something like that. That's the
way that someone like Fodor might talk
about it.
And arguably where Chomsky has ended up
in in merge and and things like this.
Uh maybe that would give us the
inductive background from which we can
slot these emotions into different
categories. And in many ways, I mean,
this is this is kind of go you know, it
takes us all the way to something like a
connectionist network, which is that
these connectionist networks are not
completely unsupervised in the sense
that they do have prior weights.
Um
and so yes, I do think the radical
tabula rasa
Well, one I one I guess I'd have to ask
her because again, I don't want to speak
on her behalf. But I wonder whether in
steel manning her position, she might
have space for something like an innate
mechanism or innate process. Yeah, well,
you're right that our viewers or
listeners must go and watch those They
They're on
I think they're on YouTube. They're the
discussions I had with
her channel.
Yes.
Um and
so you must watch it yourself and and
form, you know, your your Let and let
her Listen to her speaking for herself
and and form your own opinion. But um
the topic that you've just mentioned did
come up. Um not very
not very It wasn't discussed in at great
length, but it came up periodically in
our two
conversations.
And
my understanding what she said is yes,
she certainly agrees that there are
these innate mechanisms
and they are instinctual behaviors or
reflexive action
not necessarily only external behaviors,
but also internal actions of
within the body.
Um but
um
all that's innate is those stereotyped
actions.
Um
she doesn't think or
believe
that there is a feeling that goes with
them. Um so I I given everything that I
said earlier, you can see why I think
that some of them have feeling attached
to them because that's precisely what
makes you know, I am you know,
suffocating
as opposed to I am sleepy and uh the and
and it you you you act accordingly. I
I think the feeling
attaches to the category of need
because of what feeling does.
You can I believe
well, I don't I wouldn't go into too
much detail. Let's just say so I believe
that the feeling is attached to the
innate category.
She accepts there are innate categories,
but doesn't believe that feelings are
attached to them. But here's the really
interesting point. She then says so we
then learn we make inferences about
these categories.
So the state I am in now which I have
been in before, I recognize this state.
This is called fear.
Um and that's when fear arises. Fear is
the concept the learned concept that you
apply to the state that you find
yourself in. So the first time that this
in my view the first time that this
action
this
instinctual action freezing and fleeing
occurs,
the feeling that you will have is fear.
Her
position seems to be the first time that
it happens nothing will occur mentally.
The second time that it happens, you
will recognize I've been in this
situation before I call this fear and
now you formed the concept. That's her
way of seeing it, but the crucial thing
there is there's no place for a feeling
in that. Why do you have a feeling?
You've just categorized this state as
fear.
And she says yes, indeed, it's exactly
the same as any other type of
perception. It's perceptual inference.
And um
to me that leaves qualia entirely out.
You know, it
there's no need So I asked her the
question, why then do we feel?
And she said I don't go there. That's
not a scientific question.
Yes. Well, again, people should go and
watch and I will email at Lisa again. I
emailed her and and I think she was very
very busy. She's very busy woman. I will
I will get back in contact. So I
couldn't So we're we're running out of
time. So we've got about 10 minutes
left, but I wanted to very briefly touch
upon dreams. Yes.
We haven't spoken we haven't done
anything to do with the kind of earlier
work of yours. As I said, you know,
you're very famous for discovering the
forebrain mechanisms underlying dreams
in I think the late '90s. And you wrote
in the well, it's I think it's the 2000
paper that what you're what you're
really drawing into question there is is
association of REM and dreaming. So REM
rapid eye movement sleep and and
dreaming. When that true well, well,
historically tied together and you show
in that paper that really nicely there's
this sort of double dissociation that
you can have dreams without REM and REM
without dreams.
And you said at the very end of that
paper, the biological function of
dreaming remains unknown.
This is at least partly attributable
attributable to the fact that the
function of dreaming and the equally
unknown function of REM sleep have been
conflated for more than 40 years of
research. Future studies of these
functions should be uncoupled from one
another. I was curious, one, have they
been uncoupled from one another? And
two, has that given us any purview or
insight into the function of dreaming?
Yes.
So the double disassoci- Thank you for
raising this. It's
that was my
I mean, I spent many
happy years
doing dream research. Um
and I was very fortunate in the
discoveries that I made
in that area which like most
really significant discoveries happen
purely by luck. So
it wasn't something I was looking for.
So I just want to make sure that that
people understand the double
dissociation you're talking about. It's
not only that you can dream outside of
REM and you can
be in the REM state without dreaming.
That is a is an interesting fact, but
it's a that's not that's
I think was always recognized that the
correlation between dreaming
and and REM sleep is a probabilistic
one. Um you are much more likely to be
dreaming in REM than outside of REM. Um
but
the the the
the thing that I found which was much
more interesting I thought is that
lesions which
destroy the part of the brain that
generates REM which is which is a
cholinergic system in the mesopontine
tegmentum. That
people who
who who have lost the capacity to have
the REM state because that part of the
brain is lesioned,
they continue to dream. So with no REM,
they continue to dream. And conversely,
there are patients
who lose the capacity to dream
due to a brain lesion elsewhere,
they continue to have REM sleep. That's
the double dissociation we're talking
about.
That's the gold standard as well of Yes,
indeed. And that lesion, the one that
leads to a loss of dreaming
actually there are two lesion sites, but
the interesting one
is in the mesocortical mesolimbic
dopamine circuitry. So it's a different
circuit from the the one the the one
that generates REM sleep. It's a
different neurotransmitter from the one
that modulates REM sleep. So so dreaming
as opposed to REM sleep, they correlate
with each other, but they're not the
same thing
and
there's an interesting question as to
why they should correlate with each
other because they do very highly
correlate with each other. But you can
totally dissociate them from each other
in the way that I've just described. Now
I I said which is the quotation you just
read that we don't know what the
function of dreaming is partly because
we conflated it with REM sleep. So the
research that we were doing for decades
into what is dreaming for,
the causal research that we did, the the
variable that we manipulated was REM
sleep. So you know,
it's not surprising that we never got to
the answer because we were manipulating
something that correlates with dreaming,
but isn't actually the mechanism of
dreaming. So I said at that point in the
paper that you're quoting that now that
we can see that they're two separate
mechanisms, now we can research the
mechanism and function of dreaming by
looking at the
at the at that mechanism, not this one.
And so
that was bound to lead to progress. Um
so the the
a very interesting you said so has
progress been made?
A lot of progress has been made and in
fact when I said I spent many happy
years in a sleep lab, I in fact still
I'm doing some research in that area and
so there's one
study that's still ongoing
that I've got only the I've only
completed the pilot study for it, but
we're now doing the main study. But the
findings were so dramatic in the in the
pilot study that I feel able to say a
thing or two about them. Um the but it's
not really in the active inference
framework. So I don't know
No, no, no, no, no. Go, go, go, please.
It it can be linked and you know, Carl
and and Hobson
Carl Friston and Allan Hobson wrote some
very interesting papers within the
active inference framework
about dreaming.
Um but the the first thing to say is
that
the this mesocortical mesolimbic
dopamine system which clearly is the
the driving mechanism the causal
mechanism of dreaming. There's all sorts
of every method we've thrown at it, you
know, single cell recordings,
microdialysis,
pharmacological probes, lesion studies,
positron emission tomography, everything
everything points to that system that
system that system. That's the one that
causes the dream state.
Um the
the really interesting thing about it
is that it is
it's been called
by Panksepp who you mentioned earlier,
the seeking system. You know, the
instinctual behavior that attaches to
this system is foraging, exploratory
interest and curiosity.
It's it it it drives the most sort of
intense exploratory foraging behaviors
that an animal is capable of. And when
you look at the dreaming brain for
example, by positron emission
tomography, it's really quite
astonishing to see this system is lit up
like a Christmas tree, but you're
asleep. You know, it's like, what the
hell? How can how can this how can this
creature be asleep or this person be
asleep? If you weren't told that they
were asleep and you just looked at that
at that
at that brain image, you would say
this person's
you know, manic and and high on cocaine
or something, you know?
That's the first thing that's that I
think is really interesting is that
the
the mechanism that drives the dream is a
is an intensely motivated active state.
and so the the the the the first a step
toward a
an understanding of why do we dream
has to be
you have to start there, you know, why
do we have these intense activated
motivated states while we're sleeping?
And secondly, why don't we wake up when
we have them?
Um so
um one way of thinking
is that the dream happens instead of
real behavior. You have you have a
virtual reality in which you are
in which you are imagining or deluding
yourself
that you are acting on your motivated
states. Why these motivated states have
to happen while you're asleep is another
question, but the fact that they do
happen is is obviously physiologically
demonstrably true. So
uh
the the this state is acted on in the
virtual hallucinatory reality of the
dream rather than in real reality
because
to act on them in in reality would be
incompatible with the state of sleep. So
that is a that is a I think a
a very simple and reasonable hypothesis
as to why do we dream? We dream so that
we can stay asleep during this highly
motivated states of mind that occurs
state of mind and body that if if it
weren't for the fact that we're
paralyzed we would be running around
like lunatics. So you you don't run
around like a lunatic you
because you're running around in your
dreams you
So how do you test that hypothesis? I
said earlier that there are two lesion
sites which lead to cessation of
dreaming and we've spoken only about the
one. The other one is damage to the
visual visuospatial cortices at the back
of the brain.
If you can't generate the
mental image the heteromodal and
predominantly visual but not only visual
imagery
that is the dream then how can you
dream? So
they theoretically less interesting
those patients they stop dreaming due to
occipital parietal strokes.
Um
but if the prediction that I've just
made the hypothesis I've just formulated
as to what the function of dreaming is
if it were correct then these patients
who can't generate the hallucinated
reality because they because of those
those lesions they should wake up.
They should have very bad sleep.
When the when this arousal state occurs
it should wake them up. So that's the
prediction that I tested in my pilot
study and let me tell you I have never
seen worse polysomnographs than in these
patients.
Yeah, so I I think we're on to something
there that what what dreams do is they
enable you to stay asleep by by
letting off steam letting off
motivational steam in a in an
hallucinatory world rather than the real
world. I'm not saying that's the
function but that's a function.
That's very cool. That's very cool.
People have to keep their eyes out for
that for those sets of papers.
Mark, this was awesome. We covered so
much ground.
I'm I'm really really very grateful
indeed. I always like to ask people just
to say at the very end where people can
find them if they have you know if
people have questions or people want to
read your work, how can people reach out
to you or where should they find your
work?
So
to contact me you can contact me by
email.
It's just my name mark.solms@uct
University of Cape Town.ac
academic.za
which is South Africa. So
mark.solms@uct.ac.za.
I am also for my sins on what used to be
called Twitter but's now called
something else that I don't want to say.
So
there I'm mark_solms
@mark_solms.
We'll make sure to put your Google
Scholar and website and all this stuff
on in in the video description. Again,
Mark, thank you so so very much.
I enjoyed it. Thank you. All right.